Joel Sunday Salako

4A, Venerable Olusola Adesina Close, New Bodija Ibadan Oyo state, Nigeria (+234)-803-200-4758 joels@mtnnigeria.net; salcom j@yahoo.com; salankyjoe@gmail.com

SUMMARY

Wide-ranging experience in Ericsson GSM (BSS/NSS) installation, O & M, BTS (RBS 200 & 2000) integration, operations, and maintenance. Operations and Maintenance of Microwave Radios such as Harris Truepoint, Harris Megastar, DMC Stratex Eclipse, XP4, Altium etc. Good Experience of last mile microwave transmission link planning. A good knowledge of Tellabs and Huawei Equipment such as DXX6300, DXX8100, DXX8600 families, OSN8800, OSN3500, OSN7500, OSN9500, OSN6800, BWS1600, OSN550 etc.

Wide-ranging experience in maintenance, repairs and assembling of all grades of computers and computer peripherals as well as full proficiency over the maintenance, repairs, programming and installation of two way UHF, VHF and HF radio equipment (especially of the Motorola and Barrette models). My expertise also covers the repair and maintenance of GSM phones. I have been involved in the design and deployment of electrical and electronic equipment such as Inverters, Voltage Stabilizers, Power Supplies, Alarm Systems, Temperature Controllers, to name a few. Excellent communication skill. Ability to lead, train and maintain excellent communication with productive staff. A wide range of Telecommunications experience working with MTN Nigeria Communications Limited, the biggest mobile operator in Nigeria and West Africa and the largest subsidiary in the MTN Group.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Transmission Access Planning Engineer

June 2011 - Present

MTN Nigeria Communications Limited

- Provision of circuits routing for the new Base Transceiver Station (BTS), upgrades and re-parenting
- Provide the circuits routing for Internet Protocol (IP) network
- Developing and Planning Effective transmission network protection Methods.
- Following up with Transmission implementation unit to be sure that Multiplexers are installed according to the released WA and that Traffic cut over is carried out according to the released plans
- IP/MPLS traffic migration and integration plan (Tellabs 8600 Edge nodes)
- Planning direct connect traffic integration for Enterprise Customers
- Carry out field surveys on terrain and generate maps based on the data gathered from the surveys
- Plan microwave transmission systems for Access part of the GSM subsystem.
- Provide in-depth transmission engineering support in the resolution of Transmission faults.
- Develop work authorization for Team Lead's review.
- Provide input on decisions in upgrading Transmission Access Resources to support 2G, EDGE, 3G, Wifi and Wimax services.
- Frequency spectrum availability Management/re-use.
- ❖ Multiplexer Integration Plan for National Fiber Extension (NFE) Project.
- ❖ IP DCN Plan for Microwave Radio Network Elements
- ❖ IPRAN Based Microwave Planning and Multiplexer Design.
- Coordination of IPRAN E2E Integration/Migration Vendor Team (AVIAT & HUAWEI)

Transmission Topology Planning Engineer

April 2008 - June 2011

MTN Nigeria Communications Limited

- Provision of circuits routing for the Inter-MSC, Direct connect and Interconnect
- Planning and releasing Synchronous Digital Hierarchy (SDH) and Plesiochronous Digital Hierarchy (PDH) multiplexes and synchronization clock
- Provide the circuits routing for Internet Protocol (IP) network
- Optimization of the circuits for efficient routing and protection
- Providing Cut-over plan and Mobile Switching Centers (MSC) integration plan for connectivity
- Developing and Planning Effective network protection Methods.
- Designing network synchronization process
- Releasing Work Authorization (WA) for installation of Multiplexers on site.
- Planning for the full integration of VGC acquired fixed wired Line into MTN network (RDLU and DSLAM).

❖ IP/MPLS traffic migration and integration plan (Tellabs 8600 Edge nodes)

Field Support Engineer (FSE)

MTN Nigeria Communications Limited

August 2005 - April 2008

- ❖ Integration, acceptance & maintenance of MTN SDH backbone links
- Integration, acceptance & maintenance of MTN PDH microwave links, Ericsson and Huawei BTS sites
- Perform routine maintenance on TX (SDH (Harris Truepoint & Megastar, DMC Eclipse & Altium) and PDH (DMC stratex , XP4, DXR 700 etc) and BTS (Ericsson RBS 2000 family and Huawei BTS312 & 3012 family) equipment as defined to schedule
- Swiftly diagnose and clear any faults or alarms assigned by trouble ticket, or ensure escalation to correct parties.
- Clear faults on Antenna Systems Using Site Master.

Technical Consultant

November 2003 – August 2005

MTN Nigeria Communications Limited

- Carrying out warranty Repairs on GSM Handsets (Levels 1 & 2)
- Carrying out quality control tests on repaired handsets to ensure they are in good working condition before dispatching to customers
- Giving advice to customers on how best to use and maintain their phones for optimum performance

Bench Technician

September 2001 - November 2003

RTB telecom Ltd, Lagos, Nigeria

- ❖ Maintenance of Motorola UHF and VHF Radios such as GR500 repeaters, GM300 & 600 series, GP300 & 600 series etc
- Installation of Mobile Radios (GM140, GM160, GM300 etc.) into vehicles
- Installation of Base Radios and General Support of Motorola and Barrette (HF Radios) products
- * Ensuring smooth running of RTB tele-link base station (a telephone network employing two-way Radio System)
- Carrying out simple repair works on GSM handsets for RTB mobile workshop
- Troubleshooting and repairs of Computers, Printers, Monitors and Uninterruptible Power Supply

EDUCATION

- ❖ B.Sc Computer Science Federal University of Agriculture Abeokuta (FUNAAB) (2013)
- HND Electrical/Electronics Engineering Yaba College of Technology, Lagos, Nigeria (1998)

TRAINING

- ❖ Building and Leading the Team Training (LAGOS BUSINESS SCHOOL, NIGERIA)
- Connect 7.0 Multi Technology Training (AIRCOM INTERNATIONAL)
- Digital Network Planning and Management (RESOLVE ICT, NIGERIA)
- Huawei Optix BWS 1600g Backbone DWDM Optical Transmission System (HUAWEI TECHNOLOGIES)
- Introduction to Data Networking and IP (NOKIA SIEMENS)
- ❖ NE Series Router Introduction Training (HUAWEI TECHNOLOGIES)
- ❖ MPLS & IP Traffic Engineering Training (CENTENNIAL CAPITAL, NIGERIA)
- QoS and Differentiated Services (NOKIA SIEMENS)
- OPTIX OSN 8800 (OCS) O & M Training (HUAWEI TECHNOLOGIES (SHENZHEN, CHINA))
- SSU2000e/Time provider/Time watch Probe Training (GRINTEK, NIGERIA)
- ❖ Tellabs 6345/6350 Switch Node Operation and Element Management
- Tellabs 8100 Managed Access System
- ❖ Tellabs 6300 Ethernet over SDH Operation and Element Management
- Optix RTN Network Planning Basic Training & Optix RTN 900 Network Planning Training (Hybrid) (HUAWEI TECHNOLOGIES)
- ❖ MEF Carrier Ethernet Certified Professional Training (TELEFOCAL)
- LTE Induction Training (TELEHORIZON)
- ❖ Keys to Future Networks (OTT/NFV/SDN) (FERAB HILLTOP NIGERIA)
- Certified Business Analysis Professional (CBAP) Training (MAKINTOUCH)
- Power Business Intelligence Analysis Training (MAKINTOUCH)
- Pathloss 5 Training (FERAB HILLTOP NIGERIA)
- ATN/CX Mobile Backhaul Network Planning And Designing Training (HUAWEI TECHNOLOGIES)

ACCOMPLISHMENT

- ❖ Implementation of an Improved Purchase Process Cycle to Solve Customer Uncertainty Problem in E-Commerce
- ❖ Design and Construction of Digital Fuel Gauge with low level warning Alarm and Visual Display (1998)
- Design and Construction of Two-Way Intercom System (1994)

INTEREST AND ACTIVITIES

Listening to Music, Soccer, Reading, Table Tennis, Traveling, Analysis and Problem Solving.

REFERENCE

Available upon request